U.S. National Recovery Administration Printed Documents from the Division Review 5391
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
U.S. National Recovery Administration Printed Documents from the Division Review
1935-1941
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
U.S. National Recovery Administration (NRA)
5391
4 cubic feet
4 linear ft.
Reports.
Studies of the effect of NRA codes on various industries.
3338499
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, October 24, 2014
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 31, 2015
Biographical / Historical
The National Recovery Administration, also known as the NRA, was the first of several agencies to be established under authority of the National Industrial Recovery Act (48 Stat. 195), approved on June 15, 1933. Headed by an Administrator for Industrial Recovery (Gen. Hugh S. Johnson) and subject to the general supervision at first of a Special Industrial Recovery Board (consisting of the Attorney General, the Secretaries of Agriculture, the Interior, Commerce and Labor the Director of the Budget, the Chairman of the Federal Trade Conmission, and the Administrator for Industrial Recovery) and later of the National Emergency Council, the function of the NRA was to carry out the main provisions of title I of the Recovery Act. The program of the NRA had four main objectives: (l) To spread work by reducing the number of hours; (2) to increase consumer purchasing power by increasing total wage distribution; (3) to stop trade practices that were similar to those already recognized as legally unfair and to limit the severity of competition without raising prices so drastically as to neutralize the increase in total wages; and (4) to eliminate child labor.
As a means of attaining these objectives, the N.R.A. planned for the adoption of a series of codes of fair competition for the separate regulation of every important branch of trade and industry. During the period from July to October 1933 an intensive drive was made for signatures to the President's Reemployment Agreement and for popular support of its provisions.
An administrative staff was created in April 1934 to act in the name of the Administrator on all subjects assigned to it. This staff consisted of the Administrative Officer, the Review Officer (head of the Reviev Division, created in February 1943), a Special Assistant Administrator, an Assistant Administrator for Policy, the General Counsel (head of the Legal Division), the Economic Adviser (head of the Research and Planning division), a Publicity Adviser, and a Director of Enforcement.
On May 27, 1935, the United States Supreme Court handed down its decision in the Schechter case, invalidating all the codes and those portions of the Recovery Act upon which they were founded. In the light of this decision the NRA began at once to reduce its staff. A considerable part of its field, and headquarters personnel was retained to carry out such remnent functions as had escaped the interdict and such new duties as were assigned to the agency by Congress or the President.
A Senate Joint Resolution, approved June 14, 1935, extended title I of the Recovery Act until April 1,1935, expressly repealing, however, those parts of the original act that delegated power to the President to approve or prescribe codes of fair competition or that provided for the enforcement of such codes.
The National Recovery Administration was, of course, reorganized. The Agency was placed under an administrator and a few of the divisions continued, but on a diminished scale. Most of the remaining personnel were absorbed! by two large new divisions, the Division of Business Cooperation arid the Division of Review. The Division of Reviev was established to assemble, analyse, and report upon the statistical information and records of experience of the operations of the various trades and industries formerly subject to the codes of fair competition and to review the effects of the administration of Title I of the Recovery Act and the principles and policies put into effect under its authority.
The NRA was formally terminated on January 1, 1936, when. its Division of Review, Division of Business Cooperation, and Advisory Council were transferred to the Department of Commerce for liquidation by the following April 1. The Consumers' Division was transferred at the same time to the Department of Labor.
On April 1, 1936, the President appointed a Committee of Industrial Analysis, composed of the Secretary of Commerce as Chairman, the Secretary of Agriculture, the Secretary of Labor, and. four additional members from outside the Government to complete the work begun by the Division of Review end to "prepare for the President an adequate and final review of the effects of the administration of title I of the national Industrial Recovery Act." To assist this Committee, a Division of Industrial Economics was created in the Commerce Department. The Committee and its adjunct Division brought their work to a close in February 1937.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5699: William Bardsley Collection of United States National Recovery Administrations and National War Labor Board Printed and Mimeographed Documents
Administrative agencies -- United States -- Rules and practice; United States. National Recovery Administration.; United States. National Recovery Administration. Division of Review.
3338499
- Economic Survey of the Bituminous Coal Industry Under Free Competition and Code Regulation Volume I, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Economic Survey of the Bituminous Coal Industry Under Free Competition and Code Regulation Volume II, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- The Fertilizer Study Volume I, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- The Fishery Industry and the Fishery Codes, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Foreign Trade Study of the Forest Products Industry, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Earnings of Fishermen and of Fishing Craft: Appendix to The Fisher Industry and the Fishery Codes, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- The Men's Clothing Industry, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- National Labor Income By Months 1929-1935, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- The Motion Picture Industry, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Production, Prices, Employment and Payrolls in Industry, Agriculture, and Railway Transportation, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Textile Industry in the United Kingdom, France, Germany, Italy and Japan, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Financial and Labor Data on the Women's Neckwear and Scarf Industry, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Some Aspects of the Women's Apparel Industry, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Information Concerning Commodities: A Study in NRA and Related Experience in Control, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Design Piracy -- The Problem and its Treatment Under NRA Codes, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- The Control of Geographic Relations Under Codes of Fair Competition, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Minimum Price Regulation Under Codes of Fair Competition, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Operation of the Basing Point Provisions in the Lime Industry Code, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Price Control in the Coffee Industry, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Price Filing Under NRA Codes Volume I, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- NRA Report on the Coat and Suit Industry, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- NRA Report on the Cap and Cloth Hat Industry, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- NRA Report on Employment and Unemployment 1929 to 1935, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- NRA Report on the Automobile Industry, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- NRA Report on Wage Trends in Prosperity and Depression, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- NRA Report on Anti-Trust Laws and Unfair Competition, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- NRA Report on The Right of Individual Employees to Enforce Provisions of Collective Bargaining Agreements, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Federal Regulation Through the Joint Employment of the Power of Taxation and the Spending Power, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Possibility of Government Contract Provisions as a Means of Establishing Economic Standards, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Regulation of Industrial Relations in Australia, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- State Recovery Legislation in Aid of Federal Recovery Legislation -- History and Analysis, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- The Treaty-Making Power of the United States, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Two Studies of Certain Constitutional Powers as Possible Bases for Federal Regulation of Employer-Employee Relationships, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- The Baking Industry, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- The Boot and Shoe Manufacturing Industry, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- The Bottled Soft Drink Industry, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- The Builder's Supplies Industry, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- The Canning Industry, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- The Construction Industry, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- The Cotton Garment Industry, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- The Dress Manufacturing Industry, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- The Electrical Contracting and Manufacturing Industry, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- The Metal Industry, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- The Fishery Industry, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- The Furniture Manufacturing Industry, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- General Contractors Industry, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Graphic Arts Industry, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- The Hosiery Industry, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- The Iron and Steel Industry, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- The Leather Industry, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- The Lumber and Timber Products Industry, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Mason Contractors Industry, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- The Men's Clothing Industry, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- The Motion Picture Industry, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- The Motor Vehicle Retailing Trade Industry, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Needlework Industry in Puerto Rico, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- The Painting, Paperhanging and Decorating Industry, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Photo Engraving Industry, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- The Plumbing Contracting Industry, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- The Retail Lumber Industry, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Retail Trade, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 41)
- The Rubber Tire Manufacturing Industry, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Ship and Boat Building and Repairing Industries, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 43)
- The Silk Textile Industry, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 44)
- The Structural Clay Products Industry, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 45)
- The Throwing Industry, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 46)
- The Trucking Industry, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 47)
- The Waste Materials Trade, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 48)
- Wholesale and Retail Food Industry, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 49)
- The Wool Textile Industry, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 50)
- The Asphalt Shingle and Roofing Industry, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- The Business Furniture, Storage Equipment and Filing Supply Industry, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- The Candy Manufacturing Industry, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- The Carpet and Rug Manufacturing Industry, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- The Cement Industry, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- The Cleaning and Dyeing Trade, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- The Coffee Industry, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- The Copper and Brass Mill Products Industry, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- The Cotton Textile Industry, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- The Electrical Manufacturing Industry, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Fertilizer Industry, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- The Glass Container Industry, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Ice Industry, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- The Knitted Outerwear Industry, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Paint, Varnish, and Lacquer Manufacturing Industry, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- The Plumbing Fixtures Industry, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Rayon and Synthetic Yarn Producing Industry, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- The Salt Producing Industry, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- The Funeral Supply Industry, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- History of the Compliance Division, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- History of the Review Division, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- History of the Code of Fair Competition for the Shipbuilding and Ship repairing Industry, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- History of the Code of Fair Competition for the Ladies Handbag Industry, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Legal Aspects of Price Control, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- The So-called Model Code: Its Development and Modification, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- An Analysis of the PRA Census, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Legal Aspects of Labor Problems-- Minimum Wages, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Report of the Committee on the Economic and Social Implications of the Company Store and Scrip System, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- A Case in Code Authority Information Gathering, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Report of the Commission for the Coat and Suit Industry, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Report on the Operation of the National Industrial Recovery Act, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Hours, Wages and Employment Under the Codes, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 32)
- Prices and Price Provisions in Codes, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Tabulation of Labor Provisions in Codes Approved by August 8, 1934, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 34)
- NRA Report of the President's Committee of Industrial Analysis, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Bureau of the Census: By Divisions and States, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 36)
- WWI: Chronology of Important Events, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 37)
- Report on the Study of Natural Areas of Trade in the U.S., 1936 (Box 3, Folder 38)
- Study of Regularization of Employment and Improvement of Labor Conditions in the Automobile Industry, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 39)
- Price Filing Under NRA Codes, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Resale Price Maintenance Legislation in the United States, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Restriction of Retail Price Cutting With Emphasis on the Drug Industry, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Trade-Practice Conference Rules of the FTC, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Wage Differentials in the Cap and Cloth Hat Industry, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Data on Average Weekly and Average Hourly Earnings in Selected Manufacturing Industries, 1933-1935, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Employment, Payroll, Hours and Wages in 115 Selected Code Industries, 1933-1935 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Wages and Hours in the Fur Manufacturing Industry, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- NRA Policies, Standards and Code Provisions on Basic Weekly Hours of Work, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Migration of Selected Industries as Influenced by Area Wage Differentials in the Codes of Fair Competition, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Safety and Health Work Under NRA, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Child Labor Control Under NRA, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Agreement Under Section 4(a) and 7(b) of the NIRA, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- The Basic Code (Administrative Order No. X-61), 1936 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Code Compliance Activities of the National Recovery Administration, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- The Code Making Program of the NRA in the Territories, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Policy Statements Concerning Code Provisions and Related Subjects, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- The Content of NIRA Administrative Legislation, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- NRA Insignia, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- The President's Reemployment Agreement, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- The Prison Labor Problem Under NRA Administration and The Prison Compact, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Problem of Administration, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Relationship of NRA to Government Contracts, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- The Work of the Division Review, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Sheltered Workshops Under NRA, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 25)